A true story of courage and human dignity.
The Elephant Man is a drama, history film directed by David Lynch.
A Victorian surgeon rescues a heavily disfigured man being
mistreated by his "owner" as a side-show freak.
Behind his monstrous façade, there is revealed a person
of great intelligence and sensitivity.
Based on the true story of Joseph Merrick (called John Merrick in the
film), a severely deformed man in 19th century London.
Frederick Treves, played by Anthony Hopkins.
John Merrick, played by John Hurt.
Mrs Kendal, played by Anne Bancroft.
Carr Gomm, played by John Gielgud.
Mothershead, played by Wendy Hiller.
Bytes, played by Freddie Jones.
The Elephant Man is a 1980 historical drama film loosely based on the life of Joseph Merrick (named
"John" in the film), a severely deformed man who lived in London in the late 19th century.
A co-production between the United Kingdom and the United States, the film was directed by David Lynch, produced by Jonathan Sanger, and executive produced by Mel Brooks (who
was uncredited, to avoid audiences anticipating the film being in the vein of his comedic works, although his company Brooksfilms is in the opening credits).
It stars John Hurt, Anthony Hopkins, Anne Bancroft, John Gielgud, Wendy
Hiller, Michael Elphick, Hannah Gordon, and Freddie Jones.
The screenplay was adapted by Lynch, Christopher De Vore, and Eric Bergren from Frederick Treves' The Elephant Man and Other Reminiscences (1923)
and Ashley Montagu's The Elephant Man: A Study in Human Dignity (1971), incorporating both historical and fictionalized aspects.
It was shot in black-and-white by Freddie Francis and
featured make-up work by Christopher Tucker.
The Elephant Man was a critical and commercial success, with critics
highlighting Lynch's direction and Hurt's performance.
The film garnered several accolades including three BAFTA Awards (including Best Film),
and nominations for eight Academy Awards and four Golden Globe Awards.
After receiving widespread criticism for failing to honor the make-up effects, the Academy of Motion Picture
Arts and Sciences was prompted to create a competitive award for Best Makeup the following year.
The film explores themes of friendship, london,
england, escape, nurse, exploitation.
The tone is emotional and mind_bending.